It was an incredible surprise to me
كانت مفاجأة عظيمة بالنسبة لي
to find out that there was actually an organization that cared about both parts of my life.
لأجد أن هنالك حقا مؤسسة اهتمت بكلا الجانبين من جوانب حياتي
Because, basically,
لأني في الأساس
I work as a theoretical physicist.
أعمل كفيزيائي نظري
I develop and test models of the Big Bang,
أطور و أختبر نماذج للإنفجار العظيم
using observational data.
باستخدام بيانات الملاحظة
And I've been moonlighting for the last five years
قضيت ليالي السنوات الخمس الأخيرة
helping with a project in Africa.
أساعد في مشروع بأفريقيا
And, I get a lot of flak for this at Cambridge.
ولذلك , ألقى الكثير من الانتقاد بهذا الشأن في كامبريدج
People wonder, you know, "How do you have time to do this?" And so on.
كما تعلمون , يتساءل الكثير " من أين لك الوقت للقيام بهذا؟" , و إلى ما هنالك
And so it was simply astonishing to me
وذلك ببساطة , أثار ذهولي
to find an organization that actually appreciated both those sides.
أن أجد منظمة قدرت كلا هاذين الجانبين
So I thought I'd start off by just telling you a little bit about myself
لذلك ارتأيت أن أبدأ بالحديث قليلا عن نفسي
and why I lead this schizophrenic life.
و لماذا أخترت حياة بهذا الانفصام
Well, I was born in South Africa and my parents were imprisoned
حسنا, ولدت بجنوب أفريقيا , و سجن والدي
for resisting the racist regime.
لمقاومتهم النظام العنصري
When they were released, we left and we went as refugees to Kenya and Tanzania.
عندما أطلق سراحمها , غادرنا و ذهبنا كلاجئيين لكينيا و تنزانيا
Both were very young countries then,
كلاهما كانا بلدين فتيين آنذاك
and full of hope for the future.
و مليئين بالأمل للمستقبل
We had an amazing childhood. We didn't have any money,
عشت طفولة مدهشة. لم يكن لدينا أي مال
but we were outdoors most of the time.
و كنا في الخارج معظم الوقت
We had fantastic friends and we saw the wonders of the world,
كان لدينا أصدقاء رائعون و شهدنا عجائب الدنيا
like Kilimanjaro, Serengeti and the Olduvai Gorge.
مثل كلمنجارو , سيرينجيتي , و اولدوافي جورج
Well, then we moved to London for high school.
حسنا ,بعد ذلك انتقلنا إلى لندن لدراسة الثانوية
And after that -- there's nothing much to say about that.
و بعد ذلك -- لا شئ مثير لاخبركم عنه
It was rather dull. But I came back to Africa
كانت تجربة مملة . و لكنني عدت لأفريقيا
at the age of 17, as a volunteer teacher
و في عمر السابعة عشر , كمعلم متطوع
to Lesotho, which is a tiny country,
لتيلوسوتو , و هي بلد صغير
surrounded at that time by apartheid South Africa.
محاط آنذاك بالفصل العنصري في جنوب افريقيا
Well, 80 percent of the men in Lesotho
حسنا , ثمانون بالمئة من الرجال بتيلوسوتو
worked in the mines over the border,
عمل بالمناجم على الحدود
in brutal conditions.
في ظروف وحشية
Nevertheless, I -- as I'm sure -- as a rather irritating young, white man
ومع ذلك , أنا -- كما كنت واثق -- كشاب ابيض مزعج
coming into their village, I was welcomed with incredible hospitality and warmth.
أتى لقريتهم , أستقبلوني بترحاب و دفء عظيمين
But the kids were the best part.
و لكن الأطفال كانوا الجزء الأفضل
The kids were amazing: extremely eager and often very bright.
كان الأطفال مدهشون : شديدي الحماس و غالبا متقدي الذكاء
And I'm just going to tell you one story,
سأخبركم قصة واحدة فقط
which got through to me.
و التي تركت في أثرا
I used to try to take the kids outside as often as possible,
كنت أحاول أن آخد الاطفال خارجا كل ما أتيحت الفرصة
to try to connect the academic stuff with the real world.
محاولا أن وصل الاكاديميات مع العالم الحقيقي
And they weren't used to that.
و لم يعتادوا ذلك قبلا
But I took them outside one day and I said,
و لكن أخذتهم خارجا ذات يوم و قلت
"I want you to estimate the height of the building."
أريد تقدير طول المبنى
And I expected them to put a ruler next to the wall,
و كما توقعت منهم أن يضعوا مسطرةً على جانب الحائط
size it up with a finger, and make an estimate of the height.
يقدروا الطول بالإصبع , و يقوموا بتقدير للطول
But there was one little boy, very small for his age.
و لكن كان هنالك ولد واحد صغير , ضئيل البنية لعمره
He was the son of one of the poorest families in the village.
كان ابنا لأحد أفقر العائلات في القرية
And he wasn't doing that. He was scribbling with chalk on the pavement.
و لم يكن يفعل ذلك. كان يخربش بطبشور على الرصيف
And so, I said -- I was annoyed -- I said, "What are you doing?
و لذلك, قلت -- كنت متضايقا -- , ماذا تفعل ؟
I want you to estimate the height of the building."
أريد تقدير طول المبنى
He said, "OK. I measured the height of a brick.
قال, "حسناً. قمت بقياس طول طوبة
I counted the number of bricks and now I'm multiplying."
حسبتت الطوب و اقوم الآن بعملية الضرب
Well -- (Laughter) -- I hadn't thought of that one.
حسنا -- ( ضحك) -- لم أفكر بتلك الطريقة
And many experiences like this happened to me.
و الكثير من التجارب المشابهه حصلت لي
Another one is that I met a miner. He was home on his three-month leave from the mines.
حادثة أخرى و هي أني قابلت عاملا بالمناجم. و كان في البيت خلال إجازة الثلاثة أشهر من المناجم
Sitting next to him one day, he said, "There's only one thing that I really loved at school.
جالسا بجانبه في يوم, قال " هنالك شيئ واحد أحببتة فعلا في المدرسة"
And you know what it was? Shakespeare." And he recited some to me.
هل تعلم ما كان ؟ شكسبير . و تلا بعضا من أعماله لي
And these and many similar experiences convinced me
و هذه الخبرات و الكثير مما ماثلها أقنعني
that there are just tons of bright kids in Africa
أن هنالك أطنان من النوابغ في أفريقيا
-- inventive kids, intellectual kids --
-- أطفال قادرين على الاختراع , أطفال مفكرين --
and starved of opportunity.
و متعطشين للفرصة
And if Africa is going to get fixed, it's by them, not by us.
و إن كان لأفريقيا أن تصلح , فبهم , و ليس بنا
Well, after -- (Applause) -- that's the truth.
حسنا , بعد -- (تصفيق) -- هذه الحقيقة
Well, after Lesotho, I traveled across Africa
حسنا , بعد ليسوتو , جبت قاطعا أفريقيا
before returning to England
قبل العودة لإنكلترا
-- so gray and depressing, in comparison.
-- رمادية و تبعث على الإكتئاب بالمقارنة
And I went to Cambridge. And there, I fell for theoretical physics.
و ذهبت إلى كامبريدج . و هنالك وقعت بحب الفيزياء النظرية
Well, I'm not going to explain this equation,
حسنا , لن أقوم بشرح هذه المعادلة
but theoretical physics is really an amazing subject.
و لكن الفيزياء النظرية موضوع مدهش حقا
We can write down all the laws of physics we know in one line.
نستطيع أن نكتب كل قوانين الفيزياء التي نعرف في سطر واحد
And, admittedly, it's in a very shorthand notation.
و على سبيل الإعتراف , هي بتدوين شديد الإقتضاب
And it contains 18 free parameters,
و تحوي ثماني عشرة عامل حر
OK, which we have to fit to the data.
حسنا , و الذي يجب أن يناسب البيانات
So it's not the final story,
لذلك فإنها ليست نهاية القصة
but it's an incredibly powerful summary of everything we know
و لكنها ملخص شديد القوة لكل ما نعرف
about nature at the most basic level.
عن الطبيعة على أكثر أشكالها أساسية
And apart from a few very important loose ends, which you've heard about here --
و بعيدا عن القليل من النهايات الغير مكتملة المهمة جدا , و التي سمعتم عنها هنا --
like dark energy and dark matter --
كالطاقة المظلمة و المادة المظلمة --
this equation describes,
هذه المعادلة تصف --
seems to describe everything about the universe and what's in it.
على ما يبدو تصف كل شيئ يتعلق بالكون و ما فيه
But there's one big puzzle remaining,
و لكن هنالك لغز و احدٌ باقٍ
and this was most succinctly put to me by my primary school math teacher in
و كان و بأشد اقتضاب و صل إلى على يد معلمة رياضيات في مدرسة في
Tanzania, who's a wonderful Scottish lady
تنزانيا , و هي سيدة اسكتلندية رائعة
who I still stay in touch with.
و التي لا أزال على تواصلٍ معها
And she's now in her 80s.
و هي الآن في ثمانينياتها
And when I try to explain my work to her, she waved away all the details, and she said,
و حين أحاول أن أشرح عملي لها , أشاحت عنها كل تفصيلاته , و قالت
"Neil, there's only one question that really matters.
"نييل , هنالك سؤال واحد مهم في الحقيقة
What banged?" (Laughter)
ما الذي انفجر ؟ " (ضحك)
"Everyone talks about the Big Bang. What banged?"
" الكل يتكلم عن الإنفجار الكبير . ما الذي انفجر ؟"
And she's right. It's a question we've all been avoiding.
و هي محقة . هو سؤال لطالما تحاشيناه
The standard explanation is that the universe somehow sprang into existence,
التفسير المعياري هو أن الكون و بطريقةٍ ما إنشطر للوجود
full of a strange kind of energy
مليئ بطاقةٍ ما غربيةٍ
-- inflationary energy -- which blew it up.
-- طاقةٍ متضاخمةٍ -- و التي فجرته
But the puzzle of why the universe emerged in that peculiar state
و لكن اللغز يكمن في لماذا انبثق الكون في تلك الحالةِ بالذات
is completely unsolved.
لا توجد إجابة على الإطلاق
Now, I worked on that theory for a while, with Stephen Hawking and others.
الآن , انا عملت على النظرية لفترةٍ, مع ستيفن هوكنج و آخرين
But then I began to explore another alternative.
و لكن و بدأت أستكشف بديلا آخر
The alternative is that the Big Bang wasn't the beginning.
البديل كان أن الانفجار الكبير لم يكن البداية
Perhaps the universe existed before the bang,
لربما وجد الكون قبل الانفجار
and the bang was just a violent event in a pre-existing universe.
و أن الانفجار كان فقط حدثاً عنيفا في كون موجودٍ قبلا
Well, this possibility is actually suggested
حسنا , هذا الاحتمال مقترحٌ فعلا
by the latest theories, the unified theories,
من خلال النظريات الأحدث , النظريات الموحدة
which try to explain all those 18 free parameters
و التي تحاول شرح هذه العوامل الحرة الثماني عشرة
in a single framework, which will hopefully predict all of them.
في إطار واحد , و الذي نأمل أن يتنبأ بهم جمعيا
And I'll just share a cartoon of this idea here.
و سأشارككم رسماً كرتونيا للفكرة هنا
It's all I can convey. According to these theories,
هي جُلُ ما أستطيع إبلاغه . طبقا لهذه النظريات
there are extra dimensions of space, not just the three we're familiar with,
هنالك أبعاد أخرى في الفضاء , و ليس فقط الثلاته المعروفين لنا
but at every point in the room there are more dimensions.
و لكن في كل نقطة من الغرفة هنالك أبعاد أكثر
And in particular, there's one rather strange one,
بالتحديد , هنالك واحد حري بالاستغراب
in the most elegant unified theories we have.
في أكثر نظرياتنا أناقةَ و توحدا
The strange one looks likes this:
يبدو البعد بهذا الشكل :
that we live in a three-dimensional world.
أننا نعيش في عالم ثلاثي الأبعاد
We live in one of these worlds, and I can only show it as a sheet,
نعيش في أحد هذه العوالم , و أستطيع عرضها فقط كورقة
but it's really three-dimensional.
و لكنها في الواقع ثلاثية الأبعاد
And a tiny distance away, there's another sheet,
و على بعد ضئيل جدا , هنالك ورقة أخرى
also three-dimensional, and they're separated by a gap.
ثلاثية الابعاد أيضا , و هما مفصولتان بفجوة
The gap is very tiny, and I've blown it up so you can see it.
الفجوة ضيقة جدا , و أنا ضخمتها لتقدروا على رؤيتها
But it's really a tiny fraction of the size of an atomic nucleus.
و لكنها في الحقيقة هي نشز يسير من حجم نواة الذرة
I won't go into the details of why we think the universe is like this,
لن أدلف لتفاصيل حول لم نظن أن الكون هكذا
but it comes out of the math and trying to explain the physics that we know.
و لكن ذلك نتاج الرياضبات و محاولةُ لفهم الفيزياء التي نعرف.
Well, I got interested in this because it seemed to me that it was an obvious question.
حسنا , ما أثار اهتمامي بهذا , لما يٌظهِرُ أن هذا سؤال واضح
Which is, what happens if these two, three-dimensional worlds
و الذي هو , ما الذي قد يحدث في هاذين العالمين ثلاثيي الابعاد
should actually collide?
إذا ما اصطدما ؟
And if they collide, it would look a lot like the Big Bang.
و إذا اصطدما , فإن ذلك سيشبه كثيرا الانفجار الكبير
But it's slightly different than in the conventional picture.
و لكن يختلف قليلا عن الصورة التقليدية
The conventional picture of the Big Bang is a point.
الصورة التقليدية للإنفجار الكبير هو كنقطة
Everything comes out of a point;
كل شيئ يخرج من نقطة
you have infinite density. And all the equations break down.
لديك كثافة لامتناهية . و كل المعادلات تنكسر
No hope of describing that.
لا أمل لوصف ذلك
In this picture, you'll notice,
في هذه الصورة, ستلاحظ
the bang is extended. It's not a point.
أن الانفجار متوسع. و ليس بنقطة
The density of matter is finite, and we have a chance
مصير المادة محدود , و لدينا الفرصة
of a consistent set of equations that can describe the whole process.
لجملة منتظمة من المعادلات التي تصف العملية برمتها
So, to cut a long story short, we've explored this alternative.
و لنختصر القصة الطويلة . درسنا هذا البديل
We've shown that it can fit
و قد أوضحنا أنه من الممكن مطابقته
all of the data that we have about the formation of galaxies,
لكل البيانات التي لدينا حول تكوٌن المجرات
the fluctuations in the microwave background.
التذبذب في خلفية الموجات المصغرة
Furthermore, there's an experimental way
أكثر من هذا , هنالك طريقة تجريبية
to tell this theory, apart from the inflationary explanation that I told you before.
لنفصل هذه النظرية عن التفسير التضخمي الذي ذكرت سابقا
It involves gravitational waves.
و الذي يحوي موجات تجاذبية
And in this scenario, not only was the Big Bang not the beginning,
و في هذا السياق , لم يكن الانفجار الكبير هو البداية
as you can see from the picture,
كما ترون من الصورة
it can happen over and over again.
فإن ذلك قد يحدث مرة تلو الأخرى
It may be that we live in an endless universe,
من المحتمل أننا نعيش في كون لا متناه
both in space and in time.
في كِلا الزمان و المكان
And there've been bangs in the past, and there will be bangs in the future.
و كان هنالك انفجارات في الماضي , و سيكون هناك انفجارت في المستقبل
And maybe we live in an endless universe.
و من المحتمل أننا نعيش في كون لا متناه
Well, making and testing models of the universe
حسنا , صنع و تجريب نماذج للكون
is, for me, the best way I have of enjoying and appreciating the universe.
هو , بالنسبة لي , أفضل طريقة للاستمتاع و تقدير الكون.
We need to make the best mathematical models we can,
نحتاج لصنع أفضل نماذج رياضية نستطيع صنعها
the most consistent ones.
أكثرها توافقا
And then we scrutinize them, logically and with data.
و حين نمتحنها , منطقيا و من خلال البيانات
And we try to convince ourselves --
و حين نحاول إقناع أنفسنا --
we really try to convince ourselves they're wrong.
نحاول حقا إقناع أنفسنا أنها خاطئة
That's progress: when we prove things wrong.
هذا هو التقدم : حين نثبت خطأ الأشياء
And gradually, we hopefully move closer and closer to understanding the world.
و شيئا فشيئا , نأمل أن نقترب أكثر فأكثر من فهم العالم
As I pursued my career, something was always gnawing away inside me.
فيما سعيت في مجال عملي , تآكلني دائما شعور في داخلي.
What about Africa?
ماذا عن إفريقيا ؟
What about those kids I'd left behind?
ماذا عن الأطفال اللذين تركتهم خلفي ؟
Instead of developing, as we'd all hoped in the '60s,
بدلا من التطور , الذي أملناه في الستينيات,
things had gotten worse.
آلت الأحوال إلى الأسوأ .
Africa was gripped by poverty, disease and war.
أطبق الفقر والأمراض و الحروب على أفريقيا
This is very graphically shown by the Worldmapper website and project.
وهذا موضّح بيانياً بواسطة موقع وورلد مابر الإلكتروني .
And so the idea is to represent each country
و لذلك فأن الفكرة هو أن نمثل كل بلد
on a map, but scale the area according to some quantity.
على خريطة , و لكن نقيس المنطقة بناء على كمية ما.
So here's just the standard area map of the world.
و لذا هنا خريطة قياسية للعالم.
By the way, Africa is very large.
بالمناسبة , أفريقيا كبيرة جدا.
And the next map now shows Africa's GDP in 1960,
و الخريطة التالية الآن تظهر إجمالي الناتج المحلي لأفريقيا في عام 1960.
around the time of independence for many African states.
ما يقارب وقت استقلال الكثير من الدول الافريقية.
Now, this is 1990, and then 2002. And here's a projection for 2015.
الآن , هذا في 1990 ثم 2002. و هذا توقع ل 2015.
Big changes are happening in the world,
تغيرات كبيرة تحدث في العالم.
but they're not helping Africa.
و لكنها لا تشمل إفريقيا.
What about Africa's population? The population isn't out of proportion to its area,
ماذا عن عدد سكان أفريقيا؟ التعداد ليس منفصلاً عن مساحة المنطقة,
but Africa leads the world in deaths from often preventable causes:
و لكن تقود إفريقيا العالم في عدد الوفيات لأسباب يمكن منعها في أغلب الإحيان
malnutrition, simple infections and birth complications.
سوء التغذية , إصابات بسيطة , و مضاعفات ولادة.
Then there's HIV/AIDS. And then there are deaths from war.
و بعد ذلك الإيدز . يتلوه حالات الوفاه جراء الحروب.
OK, currently there are 45,000 people a month dying in the Congo,
حسنا , حالياً هنالك 45,000 فردا يموتون شهريا في الكونغو
as a consequence of the war
جراء الحرب هنالك
there over coltan and diamonds and other things.
على الكوبلت و الماس و أشياء اخرى.
It's still going on.
وما يزال ذلك .
What about Africa's capacity to do something about these problems?
ماذا عن قدرة إفريقيا أن تفعل شيئا حيال هذه المشاكل؟
Well, here's the number of physicians in Africa.
هذا هو تعداد الأطباء في أفريقيا
Here's the number of people in higher education.
و هذا هو تعداد خريجي التعليم العالي .
And here -- most shocking to me --
و هذا هنا -- الأكثر بعثا على الصدمة بالنسبة لي --
the number of scientific research papers coming out of Africa.
عدد أوراق البحث العلمي التي تخرج من أفريقيا.
It just doesn't exist scientifically.
انه فقط غير مبرر علميا
And this was very eloquently argued at TED Africa:
و هذا تم مناقشته بفصاحة في تيد أفريقيا:
that all of the aid that's been given
كل المعونات التي تم تقديمها
has completely failed to put Africa onto its own two feet.
فشلت في مساعدة إفريقيا لتقف على قدميها.
Well, the transition to democracy in South Africa in 1994
حسنا , التحول الى الديمقراطية في جنوب إفريقيا في 1994
was literally a dream come true for many of us.
كان حرفيا حلما قد تحقق للكثير منا.
My parents were both elected to the first parliament,
كلا والدي كانا قد انتُخِبا لمجلس النواب الأول,
alongside Nelson and Winnie Mandela. They were the only other couple.
إلى جانب نيلسون و ويني ماندلا .و الذين كانا الزوجين الآخرين الوحيدين.
And in 2001, I took a research leave to visit them.
و في 2001 . أخذت إجازة من البحث لزيارتهما.
And while I was busy working -- I was working on these colliding worlds, in the day.
و فيما كنت مشغولا بالعمل -- كنت أعمل على هذين العالَمين المتصادمين في ذلك اليوم.
But I learned that there was a desperate shortage of skills,
و علمت أن هناك نقصا شديداً في المهارات,
especially mathematical skills, in industry, in government, in education.
خاصة مهارات الرياضيات , في الصناعة , في الحكومة , في التعليم.
The ability to make and test models has become essential,
القدرة على صنع و اختبار نماذج أصبح أساسياً
not only to every single area of science today,
ليس فقط في كل مجال من مجالات العلوم اليوم
but also to modern society itself.
بل و في مجتمعنا الحديث بنفسه
And if you don't have math, you're not going to enter the modern age.
و إذا لم يكن لديك الرياضيات , لن تدخل العالم الحديث
So I had an idea. And the idea was very simple.
لذا كان لدي فكرة . فكرة كانت بسيطة جدا
The idea was to set up an African Institute for Mathematical Sciences, or AIMS.
الفكرة كانت إنشاء معهد إفريقي لعلوم الرياضيات أو آيمز
And let's recruit students from the whole of Africa,
و لنوظف طلابا من جميع أنحاء إفريقيا
bring them together with lecturers from all over the world,
و لنجمعهم بمحاضرين من جميع أنحاء العالم
and we'll try to give them a fantastic education.
و لنحاول إعطائهم تعليما رائعا
Well, as a Cambridge professor, I had many contacts.
حسنا , و كبرفسور بجامعة كمبريدج , كان لدي الكثير من المعارف
And to my astonishment, they backed me 100 percent.
و لدهشتي , دعموني 100 بالمئة
They said, "Go and do it,
قالوا لي " أذهب و قم بذلك
and we'll come and lecture."
و سنحضر و سنحاضر"
And I knew it would be amazing fun to bring brilliant students
و علمت كم سيكون متعة رائعةً أن تجمع طلاباً نابغين
from these countries -- where they don't have any opportunities -- together
من هذه البلدان , حيث لم يكن لديهم أية فرصة , معا
with the best lecturers in the world --
بأفضل المحاضرين في العالم
who I knew would come, because of the interest in Africa --
و اللذين علمت بأنهم سيحضرون , لاهتمامهم بأفريقيا.
and put them together and just let the sparks fly.
و لنضعهم معا و فقط لنشاهد الشرارت تتطاير.
So we bought a derelict hotel near Cape Town.
لذا اشترينا فندقا مهجورا قريبا من كيب تاون.
It's an 80-room Art Deco hotel from the 1920s.
هو عبارة عن80 غرفة على طراز فن الزخرفة من العشرينيات.
The area was kind of seedy, so we got an 80-room hotel for 100,000 dollars.
كانت المنطقة بائسة , لذا فقد حصلنا على فندقٍ ب80 غرفة لقاء 100,000 دولار.
It's a beautiful building. We decided we would refurbish it
إنه مبنى جميل . قررنا إعادة تعميره.
and then put out the word:
بعدها حددنا الهدف:
we're going to start the best math institute in Africa
سنقوم ببدء أفضل مؤسسة رياضيات في إفريقيا
in this hotel.
في هذا الفندق
Well, the new South Africa is a very exciting country.
حسنا , جنوب إفريقيا الجديدة بلد مثير جدا
And those of you who haven't been there, you should go.
و للذين لم يذهبوا منكم هناك قبلا , عليكم الذهاب.
It's very, very interesting what's happening.
إنه لجدُ باعثٍ على الاهتمام ما يحصل هناك
And we recruited wonderful staff,
و قد وظفنا طاقما رائعا,
highly motivated staff.
طاقم متحمس جدا.
The other thing that's happened, which was good for us, is the Internet.
شيئ آخر حصل , وكان جيدا لنا حقا , هو الإنترنت.
Even though the Internet is very expensive all over Africa,
على الرغم من كون الانترنت غاليا جدا في كافة أنحاء إفريقيا,
there are Internet cafes everywhere.
هناك مقاهي إنترنت في كل مكان.
And bright young Africans are desperate to join the global community,
و شباب إفريقيا النابغين يتطلعون للإنضمام للمجتمع العالمي,
to be successful -- and they're very ambitious.
ليكونوا ناجحين -- و هم طموحين جدا .
They want to be the next Einstein.
هم يريدون أن يكونوا آينشتاين القادم.
And so when word came out that AIMS was opening,
و عندما أُعلن أن آيمز قد بدأ بالإفتتاح
it spread very quickly via e-mail and our website.
أنتشر الخبر بسرعة كبيرة عبر البريد الإلكتروني و عبر موقعنا
And we got lots of applicants.
وراسلنا الكثير من المتقدمين
Well, we designed AIMS as a 24-hour learning environment,
حسنا , صممنا آيمز لتكون بيئة تعليمِ على مدار الساعة
and it was fantastic to start a university from the beginning.
كان رائعا بدء جامعةٍ من البداية
You have to rethink, what is the university for?
عليك أن تعيد التفكير , ما هو هدف الجامعة ؟
And that's really exciting.
و كان هذا مثيراً فعلا
So we designed it to have interactive teaching.
لذا صممناها لتحوي تعليما تفاعليا
No droning on at the chalkboard.
ليس تعليما مملا على لوح الطباشير
We emphasize problem-solving, working in groups,
ركزنا على حل المشاكل , العمل في مجموعات
every student discovering and maximizing their own potential
كل طالب يكتشف و يزيد على إمكاناته الكامنة الخاصة به
and not chasing grades.
و ليس ساعيا وراء الدرجات
Everyone lives together in this hotel -- lecturers and students --
الجميع يعيش سويةً في هذا الفندق , محاضرينَ و طلاباً
and it's not surprising at all to find an impromptu tutorial at 1 a.m.
و من غير المفاجئ أن ترى درسا مرتجلا في الواحدة فجرا.
The students don't usually leave the computer lab till 2 or 3 a.m.
و الطلاب عادة ما لا يغادرون مختبرات حواسيبهم حتى الثانية أو الثالثة فجرا.
And then they're up again at eight in the morning.
و تجدهم مستيقظين في الثامنة صباحا.
Lectures, problem-solving and so on. It's an extraordinary place.
محاضراتٍ , حل مشاكلٍ و هكذا دواليك . إنه لمكان خارق للعادة.
We especially emphasize areas of great relevance to Africa's development,
نحن نركز على كل المجالات المتعلقة بشدة بتطور مستقبل إفريقيا
because, in those areas, scientists working in Africa will have a competitive advantage.
لأن و في هذه المجالات يعمل العلماء في إفريقيا , و سيكون لديم ميزة تنافسية
They'll publish, be invited to conferences.
سينشرون , و سيدعَونَ إلى مؤتمرات.
They'll do well. They'll have successful careers.
سيقومون بعمل جيد, سيكون لديهم مستقبل مهني باهر.
And AIMS has done extremely well.
و قامت آيمز بعمل مميز فعلا .
Here is a list of last year's graduates, graduated in June,
هنا لائحة بخريجي العام الفائت , تخرجوا في يونيو ,
and what they're currently doing -- 48 of them.
و ماذا يفعلون الآن , كلهم ال48 .
And where they are is indicated over here.
و مكانهم عملهم مذكور هنا .
And where they've gone. So these are all postgraduate students.
و إلى أين ذهبوا . لذا كل هؤلاء الطلاب واصلوا دراسات عليا
And they've all gone on to master's and Ph.D. degrees in excellent places.
و كلهم حصلوا على الماجستير و الدكتوراة في أماكن ممتازة.
Five students can be educated at AIMS
يمكن تعليم خمسة طلاب في آيمز
for the cost of educating one in the U.S. or Europe.
بتكلفة تعليم طالب واحد في الولايات المتحدة أو أوروبا.
But more important, the pan-African student body
و لكن الأهم من ذلك , الهيكل الطلابي الإقريقي بأجمعه
is a continual source of strength, pride and commitment to Africa.
هو مصدر متواصل للقوة , الفخر و الإلتزام بإفريقيا
We illustrate AIMS' progress by coloring in the countries of Africa.
نظهر هنا إنتشار آيمز من خلال تلوين البلدان في إفريقيا
So here you can see behind this list.
لذا تستطيع أن ترى خلف هذه اللائحة
When a county is colored yellow, we've received an application;
عندا يكون البلد ملونا بالأصفر : تلقينا طلب التحاق
orange, we've accepted an application; and green,
برتقالي قبلنا الطلب , و بالاخضر :
a student has graduated.
تخرج طالب
So here is where we were after the first graduation in 2004.
أذن هنا كان بعد التخرج الاول في 2004
And we set ourselves a goal of turning the continent green.
و نصبنا هدفنا بأن نحوّل القارةَ إلى الأخضر
So there's 2005, -6, -7, -8.
لذا هنا 2005 , -6, -7 , -8
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We're well on the way to achieving our initial goal.
نحن في طريقنا لتحقيق هدفنا الإبتدائي
We had some of the students filmed at home before they came to AIMS.
لدينا بعض الطلاب الذي تصوروا في بلدانهم قبل قدومهم إلى آيمز
And I'll just show you one.
و سأريكم واحد فقط
Tendai Mugwagwa: My name is Tendai Mugwagwa.
تِنداي موجواجوا : إسمي تِنداي موجواجوا
I have a Bachelor of Science with an education degree.
أحمل شهادة البكالوريوس في العلوم مع شهادة تعليم
I will be attending AIMS.
سأحضر آيمز.
My understanding of the course is that it covers quite a lot.
فهمي للبرنامج أنه يغطي الكثير.
You know, from physics to medicine,
تعلمون , من الفيزياء إلى الطب,
in particular, epidemiology and also mathematical modeling.
بالأخص علم الأوبئة و كذلك التمثيل الرياضي .
Neil Turok: So Tendai came to AIMS and did very well.
نييل توروك : لذا حضرت تِندي آيمز , و أدت بشكلٍ جيد جداً.
And I'll let her take it from there.
و سأتركها تأخذكم من هنا.
TM: My name is Tendai Mugwagwa
تي إم : إسمي تِندي مجواجوا
and I was a student at AIMS in 2003 and 2004.
كنت طالبة في آيمز 2003 و 2004.
After leaving AIMS, I went on to do a master's in applied mathematics
بعد أن تخرجت من آيمز , ذهبت لأحصل على الماجستير في الرياضيات التطبيقية .
at the University of Cape Town in South Africa.
في جامعة كايب تاون في جنوب إفريقيا.
After that, I came to the Netherlands
بعد ذلك , أتيت إلى هولندا
where I'm now doing a Ph.D. in theoretical immunology.
و التي فيها أقوم بدراسة الدكتوراه في علم المناعة النظري.
Professor: Tendai is working very independently.
البرفسور : تِندي تعمل بشكل مستقل تماما
She communicates well with the immunologists at the hospital.
و تتواصل بشكل جيد مع اختصاصيي المناعة في المستشفى
So all in all I have a very good Ph.D. student from South Africa.
و في المجمل لدي طالبة دكتوراة جيدٍ جدا من جنوب إفريقيا
So I'm happy she's here.
لذا فأنا سعيد انها هنا
NT: Another student in the first year of AIMS was Shehu.
نييل توروك: طالب آخر كان في السنة الأولى في آيمز هو شيهو
And he's shown here with his favorite high school teacher.
و يظهر هنا مع معلمةِ الثانوية المفضل
And then entering university in northern Nigeria.
و بعد ذلك و هو يدخل جامعة شمالي نيجيريا
And after AIMS, Shehu wanted to do high-energy physics,
و بعد آيمز , شيهو أراد أن يدرس فيزياء الطاقة العالية
and he came to Cambridge.
و قدم إلى كمبريدج
He's about to finish his Ph.D.,
و هو الآن على وشك إنهاء شهادة الدكتوراه
and he was filmed recently with someone you all know.
و قد صُور حديثا مع شخصٍ تعرفونه جميعا
Shehu: And from there we will be able to,
شيهو : و من هنا سنكون قادرين على
hopefully, make better predictions and then we compare it
نأمل أن نقوم بتوقعات و من ثمَ نقوم بمقارنتها
to the graph and also make some predictions.
للرسم البياني و أيضا بعض التوقعات
Stephen Hawking: That is nice.
ستيفن هوكنج : هذا جميل
NT: Here are the current students at AIMS. There are 53 of them
نييل توروك : هنا الطلاب الحاليين في آيمز . هناك 53 منهم
from 20 different countries, including 20 women.
من 20 بلدا مختلفا , بينهم 20 من النساء.
So now I'm going to get to my TED business.
لذا سأدخل الآن في صلب عمل تيد.
Well, we had a party. This is Africa --
حسنا , كنا في حفل , هذه هي إفريقيا
we have good parties in Africa. And last month, they threw a surprise party for me.
كان لدينا حفلات جميلة في إفريقيا . و الشهر الماضي , أقاموا لي حفلاً مفاجئً
Here's somebody you've seen already.
هنا شخصٌ سبق و رأيتموه
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I want to point out a few other exceptional people in this picture.
أريد أن أشير لعدة اشخاص استثنائيين في هذه الصورة
So, we were having a party,
كنا في الحفل
as you can see they're completely eclipsing me at this point.
كما ترون إنهم يطمسون صورتي تماما في هذه النقطة
This is Ezra. She's from Darfur.
هذه إسراء . هي من دارفور
She's a physicist, and somehow stays smiling,
أنها فيزيائية , و بطريقة ما تبقى مبتسمةٌ على الدوام
in spite of everything going on back home.
على الرغم من كل ما يجري في موطنها
But she wants to continue in physics, and she's doing extremely well.
و لكنها تريد أن تكمل مشوارها في الفيزياء و هي تقوم بعمل ممتاز جدا
This is Lydia. Lydia is the first ever woman
هذه ليديا . ليديا هي المرأة الأولى على الإطلاق
to graduate in mathematics in the Central African Republic.
المتخرجة في الرياضيات في جمهورية إفريقيا المتوسطة
And she's now at AIMS. (Applause)
و هي الآن في آيمز. (تصفيق)
So now let me get to our TED wish.
الآن أسمحوا لي أن أتقدم بأمنية تيد
Well, it's not my TED wish; it's our wish, as you've already gathered.
هي ليست أمنية تيد الخاصة بي , أنها أمنيتنا , بما أننا اجتمعنا هنا معا
And our wish has two parts:
و أمنيتنا لها جانبان :
one is a dream and the other's a plan. OK.
الجانب الأول هو حلم و الآخر خطة. حسنا
Our TED dream is that the next Einstein will be African. (Applause)
حلم تيد خاصَتُنا هم أن يكون آينشتاين التالي من إفريقيا. (تصفيق)
In striving for the heights of creative genius,
مع سعينا الحثيث لسمو عبقريٍ خلاق
we want to give thousands of people the motivation,
نريد أن نمنح الآلاف من الناس الدافع
the encouragement and the courage
و التشجيع و الشجاعة
to obtain the high-level skills they need to help Africa.
ليكتسبوا المهارات التي تلزمهم ليساعدوا إفريقيا
Among them will be not only brilliant scientists --
بينهم لن يكون هنالك فقط علماء عباقرة
I'm sure of that from what we've seen at AIMS --
أنا متأكد مما رأينا في آيمز
they'll also be the African Gates, Brins and Pages of the future.
سيكون هناك غايتس أفارقة براينز و بايجز في المستقبل
Well, I said we also have a plan. And our plan is quite simple.
حسنا , أنا قلت أيضا أن هنالك خطة . و خطتنا في الحقيقة بسيطة
AIMS is now a proven model.
آيمز الآن هي نموذج مثبَت
And what we need to do is to replicate it.
و ما نريد أن نفعله هو إستنساخ التجربة
We want to roll out 15 AIMS centers in the next five years, all over Africa.
نريد أن ننشي 15 مركز آيمز في الخمس سنوات المقبلة , في كل إفريقيا
Each will have a pan-African student body,
في كل منها سيكون هنالك هيكل طلابي من كافة أنحاء إفريقيا
but specialize in a different area of science.
و لكن يتخصص في نواح مختلفةٍ من مناح العلوم
We want to use science to overcome the national and cultural barriers,
نريد أن نستخدم العلم لنتجاوز به الخلافات الثقافية و الوطنية
as it does at AIMS.
كما يقوم به آيمز الآن
And we want to add elements to the curriculum.
و نريد إضافة عناصر للمنهاج
We want to add entrepreneurship and policy skills.
نريد ان نضيف روح الإقدام و مهارات السياسات
The expanded AIMS will be a coherent pan-African institution,
آيمز الممتد سيكون مؤسسة تماسك لكل الإفريقيين
and its graduates will form a powerful network,
و خريجوها سيشكلون شبكة قوية
working together for peace and progress across the continent.
يعملون معا للسلام و التقدم لكل القاره
Over the last year,
خلالَ العام المنصرم
we've been visiting sites in Africa,
كنا نزور مواقع شتى في إفريقيا
looking at potential sites for new AIMS centers.
نبحث عن مواقع جديدة محتملة لمراكز آيمز
And here are the ones we've selected.
و هذه ما وقع عليه اختيارنا
And each of these centers has a strong local team,
و كل من هذه المواقع فيه فريق محلي قوي
each is in a beautiful place, an interesting place,
كل منها في موقع جميل , موقع مثير للاهتمام
which international lecturers will be happy to visit.
و التي سيُسعَدُ المحاضرون العالميون بزيارتها
And our partners across Africa are extremely enthusiastic about this.
و شركاؤنا في كل إفريقيا يملؤهم الحماس لهذا
Everyone wants an AIMS center in their country.
كل شخص يريد مركز آيمز في بلده
And last November,
و في نوفمبر الماضي
the conference of all the African ministers of science and technology,
في مؤتمر وزراء إفريقيا للعلوم و التكنولوجيا
held in Mombasa, called for a comprehensive plan to roll out AIMS.
الذي عقد في ممباسا , دعا لخطة شاملة لنشر آيمز
So we have political support right across the continent.
لذن فلدينا دعم سياسي على مستوى القارة
It won't be easy.
لن يكون أمرا سهلا
At every site there will be huge challenges.
في كل موقع ستكون هناك عقبات جمة
Local scientists must play leading roles
على العلماءِ المحليين أن يلعبوا دورا قائدا
and governments must be persuaded to buy in.
و يجب السعي لاقناع الحكومات بالاشتراك
Conditions are very difficult,
الشروط صعبة
but we cannot afford to compromise on those principles which made AIMS work.
و لكننا لا نستطيع المساومة على هذه المبادئ التي أنجحت آيمز
And we summarize them this way:
و لنلخصهم بهذه الطريقة:
the institutes have got to be relevant, innovative,
على المؤسسات أن تكون ذات صلة , خلاقة
cost-effective and high quality. Why?
فاعلة الكلفة و ذات جودة عالية . لم ؟
Because we want Africa to be rich.
لأننا نريد ثراء إفريقيا
Easy to remember the basic rules we need.
من السهل أن نتذكر القواعد الأساسية التي نريد
So, just in ending, let me say the only people who can fix Africa
لذا و في الختام دعوني أقول أن الوحيدين القادرين على إصلاح إفريقيا
are talented young Africans.
هم موهوبوا إفريقيا اليافعين.
By unlocking and nurturing their creative potential,
من خلال فتح الأبواب و تغذية الروح الخلاقة الكامنة
we can create a step change in Africa's future.
نستطيع أن نخلق خطوة تغيير في مستقبل إفريقيا.
Over time, they will contribute to African development
و مع الوقت سيسهمون في تطور إفريقيا
and to science in ways we can only imagine.
و للعلم بطرق نستطيع فقط أن نتخيلها.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)